<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE xep SYSTEM 'xep.dtd' [
  <!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM 'xep.ent'>
%ents;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='xep.xsl'?>
<xep>
<header>
  <title>Multi-User Chat Extensions</title>
  <abstract>This specification definies optional extensions to Multi-User Chat (XEP-0045).</abstract>
  <legal>
    <copyright>This XMPP Extension Protocol is copyright (c) 1999 - 2014 by the XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF).</copyright>
    <permissions>Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of this specification (the &quot;Specification&quot;), to make use of the Specification without restriction, including without limitation the rights to implement the Specification in a software program, deploy the Specification in a network service, and copy, modify, merge, publish, translate, distribute, sublicense, or sell copies of the Specification, and to permit persons to whom the Specification is furnished to do so, subject to the condition that the foregoing copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the Specification. Unless separate permission is granted, modified works that are redistributed shall not contain misleading information regarding the authors, title, number, or publisher of the Specification, and shall not claim endorsement of the modified works by the authors, any organization or project to which the authors belong, or the XMPP Standards Foundation.</permissions>
    <warranty>## NOTE WELL: This Specification is provided on an &quot;AS IS&quot; BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, express or implied, including, without limitation, any warranties or conditions of TITLE, NON-INFRINGEMENT, MERCHANTABILITY, or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. In no event shall the XMPP Standards Foundation or the authors of this Specification be liable for any claim, damages, or other liability, whether in an action of contract, tort, or otherwise, arising from, out of, or in connection with the Specification or the implementation, deployment, or other use of the Specification. ##</warranty>
    <liability>In no event and under no legal theory, whether in tort (including negligence), contract, or otherwise, unless required by applicable law (such as deliberate and grossly negligent acts) or agreed to in writing, shall the XMPP Standards Foundation or any author of this Specification be liable for damages, including any direct, indirect, special, incidental, or consequential damages of any character arising out of the use or inability to use the Specification (including but not limited to damages for loss of goodwill, work stoppage, computer failure or malfunction, or any and all other commercial damages or losses), even if the XMPP Standards Foundation or such author has been advised of the possibility of such damages.</liability>
    <conformance>This XMPP Extension Protocol has been contributed in full conformance with the XSF's Intellectual Property Rights Policy (a copy of which may be found at &lt;<link url='http://xmpp.org/extensions/ipr-policy.shtml'>http://xmpp.org/extensions/ipr-policy.shtml</link>&gt; or obtained by writing to XSF, P.O. Box 1641, Denver, CO 80201 USA).</conformance>
  </legal>
  <number>xxxx</number>
  <status>ProtoXEP</status>
  <type>Standards Track</type>
  <sig>Standards</sig>
  <approver>Council</approver>
  <dependencies>
    <spec>XMPP Core</spec>
    <spec>XEP-0045</spec>
  </dependencies>
  <supersedes/>
  <supersededby/>
  <shortname>NOT_YET_ASSIGNED</shortname>
  <author>
    <firstname>Florian</firstname>
    <surname>Schmaus</surname>
    <email>flo@geekplace.eu</email>
    <jid>flo@geekplace.eu</jid>
  </author>
  <revision>
    <version>0.0.1</version>
    <date>2015-05-12</date>
    <initials>fs</initials>
    <remark><p>First draft.</p></remark>
  </revision>
</header>
<section1 topic='Introduction' anchor='intro'>
  <p>This XEP provides some useful optional extensions to &xep0045;.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Requirements' anchor='reqs'>
  <p>STRONGLY RECOMMENDED.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Determing Support' anchor='disco'>
    <p>An entity may wish to discover if a service implements the Multi-User Chat protocol and the optional extensions defined in this XEP; in order to do so, it sends a service discovery information ("disco#info") query to the MUC service's JID.</p>
    <example caption='Entity Queries Chat Service for MUC Support via Disco'><![CDATA[
<iq from='hag66@shakespeare.lit/pda'
    id='lx09df27'
    to='chat.shakespeare.lit'
    type='get'>
  <query xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/disco#info'/>
</iq>]]></example>
    <p>The service MUST return its identity and the features it supports.</p>
    <example caption='Service Returns Disco Info Result'><![CDATA[
<iq from='chat.shakespeare.lit'
    id='lx09df27'
    to='hag66@shakespeare.lit/pda'
    type='result'>
  <query xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/disco#info'>
    <identity
        category='conference'
        name='Shakespearean Chat Service'
        type='text'/>
    <feature var='http://jabber.org/protocol/muc'/>
    <feature var='urn:xmpp:muc:mid'/>
    <feature var='urn:xmpp:muc:pmtag'/>
  </query>
</iq>]]></example>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Extensions' anchor='extensions'>
  <section2 topic='Unique and stable message IDs' anchor='mid'>
	<p>
	  If the MUC service announces support for the 'urn:xmpp:muc:mid' feature, then he MUST handle the &lt;message-id/&gt; element as defined in TODO XEP-MID. Client can send messages with the &lt;message-id/&gt; extension element. Message Stanzas send from the MUC service to MUC participants MUST contain a unique and stable message ID witin &lt;message-id/&gt; element.
	</p>
	<example caption='A message stanza with the message ID extension.'><![CDATA[
<message xmlns='jabber:client'
         to='room@muc.example.org'
         type='groupchat'>
  <body>Typical body text</body>
  <message-id xmlns='urn:xmpp:mid:0' client-id='de305d54-75b4-431b-adb2-eb6b9e546013'/>
</message>]]></example>
	<p>
	  The server MAY override the ID. If so, the "message-id" element MUST contain an "id" <em>and</em> a "client-id" attribute.
	</p>
	<example caption='A message stanza with the message ID extension.'><![CDATA[
<message xmlns='jabber:client'
         to='room@muc.example.org'
         type='groupchat'>
  <body>Typical body text</body>
  <message-id xmlns='urn:xmpp:mid:0'
              id='new-id-overrides-client-id'
              client-id='de305d54-75b4-431b-adb2-eb6b9e546013'/>
</message>]]></example>
	<p>
	  Otherwise, if the server does not override the ID, he MAY omit the "client-id" attribute.
	</p>
  </section2>
  <section2 topic='Taging private MUC messages' anchor='pmtag'>
	<p>
	  If the MUC service announces support for the 'urn:xmpp:muc:pmtag' feature, then he MUST tag private MUC messages with a &lt;x/&gt; element qualified by the 'http://jabber.org/protocol/muc#user' namespace before sending it to the recipient (see XEP-45 ยง 7.5 Sending a Private Message).
	</p>
	<example caption='Tagged private MUC message'><![CDATA[
<message
    from='coven@chat.shakespeare.lit/firstwitch'
    id='hgn27af1'
    to='crone1@shakespeare.lit/desktop'
    type='chat'>
  <body>I'll give thee a wind.</body>
  <x xmlns='http://jabber.org/protocol/muc#user'/>
</message>]]></example>
	<p>
	  This allows clients receiving the message by e.g. carbon copies to determine that it's a MUC private message.
	</p>
  </section2>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Business Rules' anchor='rules'>
  <p>OPTIONAL.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Implementation Notes' anchor='impl'>
  <p>OPTIONAL.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Accessibility Considerations' anchor='access'>
  <p>OPTIONAL.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Internationalization Considerations' anchor='i18n'>
  <p>OPTIONAL.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='Security Considerations' anchor='security'>
  <p>REQUIRED.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='IANA Considerations' anchor='iana'>
  <p>REQUIRED.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XMPP Registrar Considerations' anchor='registrar'>
  <p>REQUIRED.</p>
</section1>
<section1 topic='XML Schema' anchor='schema'>
  <p>REQUIRED for protocol specifications.</p>
</section1>
</xep>
